Suchismit Mahapatra

SENIOR AI SCIENTIST/ENGINEER · (MACHINE LEARNING | DEEP LEARNING

LinkedIn, Sunnyvale, CA

□716-435-8865 | ☑suchismi@buffalo.edu | 备https://schrilax.github.io/ | 🛅 suchismit | 🚵 schrilaxs | ☑suchismit

About Me

I am a Senior AI Scientist/Engineer with LinkedIn, applying different ML/DL, GNN and NLP techniques to solve related problems. I have 10+ years of research and 5 years of developer experience during which I have worked on a variety of problems.

Research Interests

My research focuses on designing and implementing novel algorithms which enable large-scale learning and includes:

- Machine/Deep Learning (ML/DL)
- Natural Language Processing (NLP)

- Deep Graph/Geometric Learning (GNN)
- Nonlinear/Distributed Optimization

Academic Background

muniversity of Buffalo, The State University of New York

April 2012 - June 2018

September 2010 - June 2012

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Topic: Scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods for streaming data.
- Advisors: Varun Chandola, Nils Napp & Jaroslaw Zola | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 (Transcript)

muniversity of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

Buffalo, NY

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Topic: A Cold Start Recommendation System Using Item Correlation and User Similarity. 🔼
- Advisor: Rohini Srihari | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 | Department rank: 1 out of 555 (Transcript)

m National Institute of Technology, Rourkela

Rourkela, India

August 2001 - May 2005

B.Tech. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Specialization: Discrete Mathematics and Algorithms
- Cumulative Score: 77% (First class with Honors)(Transcript) | Joint Entrance Exam Rank 22 out of 400,000

Honors _

2022	Completed NLP / NLU and RL courses as part of AI certification from Stanford University.	Sunnyvale, CA
2022	Was invited to and attended the prestigious 2022 CIFAR DLRL School and OxML 2022.	Sunnyvale, CA
2021	PC member for ICLR (2021 - present), ACL (2021 - present) and NeurIPS (2021 - present).	Sunnyvale, CA
2020	Was invited to and attended the prestigious Theory of Reinforcement Learning program.	Berkeley, CA
2019	PC member for ICML (2020 - present) and EMNLP 2021.	Palo Alto, CA
2019	Was invited to and attended the prestigious Foundations of Deep Learning program.	Berkeley, CA
2016	Became a NVIDIA GPU Educator.	Santa Clara, CA

Skills & Proficiencies _____

Python | PyTorch | TensorFlow | Keras | C/C++ | Apache MapReduce | Scala | CUDA | Hive

Research Experience _____

LinkedIn Sunnyvale, CA

SENIOR AI SCIENTIST/ENGINEER

July 2021 - Present

March 2020 - July 2021

- Knowledge Graph (KG)/Special Interest Group (SIG)
 - Tech Lead for KG/SIG teams (10+ engineers), applying different ML/DL, GNN and NLP techniques to solve related problems.

Amobee Redwood City, CA

• Developed a novel bidding strategy based on Win Price (WP) estimation

- Developed and productionized a novel bidding strategy using nonlinear ML based approaches for estimating WP.
- Built a Factorization Machine (FM/FFM) based ML pipeline for usage in production
 - Led efforts to build a FM/FFM based ML pipeline using a novel sparse matrix formulation that can handle high modality features.
- Incorporating user embeddings into existing ML/DL models to improve performance
 - Trained BERT/GAN based generative models to construct user embeddings for usage by our existing models.

NOVEMBER 16, 2022

SCIENTIST I

Criteo Al Lab Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST

July 2018 - December 2019

- Improve Click-through and Sales prediction
 - Enhanced existing production Click-through and Sales prediction pipeline using nonlinear ML techniques. Improved stability of our new models significantly from +50% to +5%. A/B test using new models resulted in +3-6% uplift in long-term RexT on all platforms.
- Theoretical aspects of Deep Learning (worked with Noureddine El Karoui)
 - Working towards understanding kernel and manifold specific aspects of theoretical deep learning.
- Resolving the posterior-collapse issue in Seq2Seq learning
 - Developed a quantization based approach towards resolving the posterior-collapse issue. 🔼

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Kernel Manifold Learning (worked with Varun Chandola)
 - Developed novel manifold Learning techniques motivated from Gaussian Processes.

Criteo AI Lab Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

May 2017 - December 2017

January 2018 - May 2018

- Cross-domain Query-Product (QP) modeling (worked with Suju Rajan)
 - Developed a robust QP model across retailer domains via Domain Adaptation and Optimal Transport based approaches. 🗗

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT January 2017 - May 2017

- Representation learning via DL/NLSDR methods (worked with Varun Chandola / Nils Napp / Jaroslaw Zola)
 - Interpreting complex nonlinear processes using DL/NLSDR methods. 🔼 🛗 🛗

BD Biosciences San Jose, CA

MACHINE LEARNING ALGORITHM DESIGN INTERN

- Fast Clustering of Flow Cytometry (FC) data
 - Upscaled BD's clustering framework for high dimensional FC data upto ~16x.

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

June 2016 - August 2016

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

June 2013 - December 2015

- Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction (worked with Varun Chandola / Jaroslaw Zola / Nils Napp)
 - Developed scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods in a streaming setting.

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

June 2011 - August 2012

• Localization via Entropy Reduction (worked with Robert Platt)

- Developed a novel active localization technique via sequential reduction of entropy using OpenRAVE/ROS.

Publications

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- 1. New Methods & Metrics for LFQA tasks. S. Mahapatra, V. Blagojevic and P. Bertorello. 2021 (Preprint available) Interpretable Graph Similarity Computation via Differentiable Optimal Alignment of Node Embeddings. K. Doan, S. Manchanda, S.
- 2. Mahapatra and C. Reddy. Proceedings of the 44th International ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval, 2021 🔼
- Discretized Bottleneck in VAE: Posterior-Collapse-Free Sequence-to-Sequence Learning. Y. Zhao, P. Yu, **S. Mahapatra**, Q. Su and C. Chen. 2020 (Preprint available)
- 4. Learning Manifolds from Non-stationary Streaming Data. S. Mahapatra and V. Chandola. 2019 (Preprint available) 🔀
- S-Isomap++: Multi Manifold Learning from Streaming Data. **S. Mahapatra** and V. Chandola. Proceedings of 5th IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2017
- **6.** Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. **S. Mahapatra**, F. Schoeneman, V. Chandola, J. Zola, N. Napp. Proceedings of SIAM Data Mining Conference, 2017
- Modeling Graphs Using a Mixture of Kronecker Models. **S. Mahapatra** and V. Chandola. Proceedings of the 3rd IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2015.

Certifications _

2022	Natural Language Processing with Transformers 🔼	Hugging Face
2022	Mastering Model Deployment and Inference 🔼	Sphere
2022	Driving Business Impact with Machine Learning 🔼	Sphere
2021	Building Transformer-Based Natural Language Processing Applications 🔼	NVIDIA DLI